A Guide to the Algernon B. Chandler, Jr. Records, 1919 -1928
Simpson Library, University of Mary Washington
Special Collections and University Archives, Simpson Library, University of Mary Washington
Algernon B. Chandler, Jr. Records, 1919 -1928
Special Collections and University Archives, Simpson Library, Univeristy of Mary Washington
0004
18 folders.
Chandler, Jr., Algernon B.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The materials were transferred from the Presidents Office to the University Archives.
Biographical Information
Algernon B. Chandler, Jr.
President, 1919-1928
Fredericksburg State Normal and Industrial School for Women (1919-1924)
Fredericksburg State Teachers College (1925-1928)
Algernon Bertrand Chandler, Jr. was born in Bowling Green, Virginia on May 12, 1870. He attended the University of Virginia for both his undergraduate and graduate degrees. He then took and passed a course in law at Washington and Lee University, after which he practiced law in Atlanta with his brother. He made his return to academia after leaving law and began his teaching career at several private schools in Richmond: Locust Dale Academy, Nolleys School for Boys, and Miss Elletts School for Girls (later St. Catherines School). After leaving private education for public, he served as principal of Clifton Forge grade and high school, then returned to Richmond as principal of Leigh Public School for six years. During this time he gradually made his way to higher education by teaching evening English classes at the Virginia Mechanics Institute. He also served as a state school examiner and the secretary of that board.
In 1909, President Edward Russell hired Chandler as a professor of Latin at the new Normal School in Fredericksburg; he became Dean shortly thereafter, also serving as acting president during an illness late in President Russells term. Just under a month after President Russell resigned in May 1919, Chandler was elected to the replace him at a special meeting of the Normal School Board on June 7, 1919.
Chandler was a scholar as well as a teacher. He wrote the Virginia supplement to Fryes Grammar School Geography, which was a nationally used textbook. He also published in the magazine for the Virginia Teachers Association and served as the education editor of the Richmond News-Leader for three years.
In his nine years as president (1919-1928), Chandler faced many challenges that he met with great success. He doubled the size of the faculty, eliminated the high school curriculum to focus on college courses, and strengthened the student teaching program by establishing the College Heights High School on campus. Housed in the appropriately named Chandler Hall, this school enrolled more than 400 students from elementary through high school levels and provided practical teaching preparation.
Chandler also increased the size of the campus with a new student activities building, an open-air theater, and the Virginia Hall residence. Finally, he oversaw an institutional name change. In 1924, The Fredericksburg State Normal and Industrial School for Women became Fredericksburg State Teachers College.
Chandlers most significant challenge was due to a 1919 change in the mission of the Normal Schools as imposed by the State. In order to eliminate unnecessary duplication in programs, areas of specialization were assigned to each of the four state normal schools. While still concentrating on teacher education, Fredericksburg would focus on teaching music, industrial arts, and commercial subjects (business). It would also have the only four-year degree in commercial subjects.
In 1927, Chandler was elected to membership in Phi Beta Kappa at the University of Virginia. He was also one of the two Fredericksburg persons listed in Whos Who in America.
On September 10, 1928, at the age of 58, Chandler suffered a stroke and died while on his way home from the College. He is buried in Bowling Green. After his death, his wife Blanche sold their home to the College, and it served first as the infirmary and later was named Anne Fairfax Hall. As a testament to his commitment to higher education for women as well as an indication of his great fondness for the school that he served, Chandler willed $1,000.00 to the College to establish scholarships for the education of some worthy Junior or Senior students.
Scope and Content
The collection contains Algernon B. Chandler, Jr.s records from 1919-1928, and principally includes correspondence related to school employees and students; reports to various state education and governmental bodies; and items documenting the fundraising for and building of the Student Alumnae Services Building. Much of the correspondence in Series 1 concerns the appointments and reappointments of College faculty, and several memos are signed by the faculty members. Letters also concern disciplinary problems with students. All of the correspondence is arranged either chronologically or alphabetically by folder. Series 2 includes official reports sent to the state board that governed Virginias normal schools and teachers colleges from 1919-1928. Other reports include bound copies of the state budget bill for 1920, 1922, and 1923, and the appropriations bill for 1922, 1923, and 1924, as well as a supplemental appropriation bill for 1926. Series 3 contains materials related to the Student Alumnae Services Building. Items of note are publicity materials for the capital campaign to raise money, a sales manual used to train those soliciting donations, alumni and donor lists, and solicitation correspondence that is arranged chronologically.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Reports, and (3) Student Alumnae Services Building. Folder 1 (Faculty Appointments and Reappointments, 1920) is arranged alphabetically, with a list of names appearing in Appendix 1.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
The Bullet. Volume II, #3. January 31, 1929.
History of Mary Washington College: 1908-1972 Edward Alvey, Jr., 1996.
The Second President, 1919-1928 MWC Today. Winter1983.
Appendix 1: Faculty appointments and reappointments, 1920
Atkinson, Eula H.
Black, Ethel
Chiles, J. H.
Clark, Annie G.
Crawford, Clara M.
Mathias, Margaret E.
Meyers, Mary M.
Ninde, M. Lousie
People, Charlotte Ross
Perrin, Miriam Stausford
Reed, Mary M.
Roberts, Lottie A.
Ruff, Dalia L.
Starke, P.
Tanner, Grace K.
Vaughen, Carrie Belke
Walker, Marie
Williams, Elizabeth
Young, M. J.
Contents List
- Series 1: Correspondence, 1920-1927
  - Faculty Appointments and Reappointments, 1920 (Folder 1)
  - Memos Regarding School Matters, 1919-1921 (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence as Dean of the College, 1913, 1922 (Folder 3)
  - Disciplinary Problems, 1926-1928 (Folder 4)
  - Student Government Officers, 1927 (Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1920-1921 (Folder 6)
- Series 2: Reports, 1919-1928
  - Virginia Normal School Board, 1919-1921 (Folder 7)
  - Virginia Normal School Board, 1922-1923 (Folder 8)
  - Board of Virginia Teachers Colleges (Formerly Virginia Normal School Board), 1927-1928 (Folder 9)
  - Budget Committee of the State Legislature, 1921 (Folder 10)
  - State Budget, 1920-1926 (Folder 11)
- Series 3: Student Alumnae Services Building, 1927-1928
  - Publicity Materials, 1917 (Folder 12)
  - Alumni and Donor Lists, undated (Folder 13)
  - Building Fund Correspondence, June-July 19, 1927 (Folder 14)
  - Building Fund Correspondence, July 20-30, 1927 (Folder 15)
  - Building Fund Correspondence, August 1-6, 1927 (Folder 16)
  - Building Fund Correspondence, August 17-31, 1927 (Folder 17)
  - Building Fund Correspondence, September-March 1928 (Folder 18)